<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>JorisL blog</title><link>http://</link><description>My personal blog</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 12:10:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>marmite</generator><item><title>Writing a simple lisp in LabVIEW and Nim</title><link>http:///writing-a-simple-lisp-in-labview-and-nim.html</link><description><![CDATA["Making my own programming language, first in LabVIEW and then in Nim."]]></description><category>programming</category><category>lisp</category><category>LabVIEW</category><category>Nim</category><guid>http:///writing-a-simple-lisp-in-labview-and-nim.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-lisp</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p>Learning how to make an interpreter for a custom programming language was a challenge I wanted to do for quite some time.
Due to it's simplicity in parsing, and the number of resources available, it was a simple choice to make the custom language a lisp-like language.</p>
<h2><a href="#labview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="labview"></a>LabVIEW</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/JorisL/labview_lisp">The first version</a> of my custom interpreter was made in LabVIEW, for the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>LabVIEW is often used at my job, but it had been a while since I programmed in it myself.
So I wanted to fresh up my knowledge.</li>
<li>There are lots of resources online, which I definitely needed to use, showing how to implement a lisp in a common language (Python, C, etc.).
Trying to implement it myself in LabVIEW, which uses a different paradigm than almost all other languages <sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn-1" id="fnref-1" data-footnote-ref>1</a></sup>, forces me to actually understand what the examples show.</li>
<li>LabVIEW is arguably one of the worst (e.g. fun) languages suited for this kind of task.
And there are examples of people implementing a lisp in <a href="https://github.com/kanaka/mal">many languages</a>, I didn't yet see anyone who implemented something like this in LabVIEW.</li>
</ul>
<p>In this version of my programming language, I was eventually able to do things as defining functions and applying those functions to data.</p>
<pre><code class="language-lisp">(do
 ; get first element from a list
 (define first
   (lambda (x)
     (nth 0 x)))

 ; get remainder of list after first element
 (define rest
   (lambda (x)
     (nthrest 0 x)))

 ; insert element at the end of a list
 (define append
   (lambda (lst elt)
     (insert lst (len lst) elt)))

 ; apply return a list with func applied to each element of lst
 (define map
   (lambda (func lst)
     (do
       (define lstout (list))
       (while (not (= lst (list)))
         (do
           (define lstout (append lstout
                                  (func (first lst))))
           (define lst (rest lst))))
       lstout)))


  (map (lambda (x) (* x x))
      (list 1 2 3 4 5 6)))

; returns (1 4 9 16 25 36)

</code></pre>
<p>However, the implementation of this language needs a lot of recursion, and the number of recursive calls to VI's is severely limited.
Therefore the complexity of the program that can run are really limited.</p>
<h2><a href="#nim" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="nim"></a>Nim</h2>
<p>After implementing an initial version in LabVIEW, I wanted to make an interpreter that would actually be capable of running 'something'.
For <a href="https://github.com/JorisL/nim_lisp">this implementation</a> I'd chosen <a href="https://nim-lang.org">Nim</a>, as it is a relatively high-level, but still quick and compiled, language.
This project was a good way of trying out the language.</p>
<p>In this version of the language I was able to add some additional functionalities, such as Macro support.
Using lisp macro's you are able to add features and structures to the language that can't be implemented as a function during execution.
See the snippet below from the 'standard library'; In the Nim interpreter I did not define how it should handle an <code>and</code> or <code>or</code> keyword,
and these cannot be implemented as functions<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn-2" id="fnref-2" data-footnote-ref>2</a></sup>.
But using macro's it is possible to define how these can be rewritten as, in this case, an if statement (which in turn is also defined as a macro).</p>
<pre><code class="language-lisp"> (define and
   (macro
    (a b)
    (quasiquote
     (if (unquote a) (unquote b) nil))))

 (define or
   (macro
    (a b)
    (quasiquote
     (if (unquote a) (unquote a) (unquote b)))))
</code></pre>
<p>In order to test that my programming language could actually do 'something', I <a href="https://github.com/JorisL/nim_lisp/blob/main/examples/bf/brainfuck.nlisp">implemented another programming language in it</a>.
Note that efficiency was not the main goal of this project 😄<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn-3" id="fnref-3" data-footnote-ref>3</a></sup>.</p>
<hr />
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
<section class="footnotes" data-footnotes>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>LabVIEW uses the dataflow programming paradigm, while most languages are instead of procedural, functional, and/or object oriented. <a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref" data-footnote-backref data-footnote-backref-idx="1" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>A function always evaluates it's arguments. For example <code>(+ 2 (* 6 7))</code> first evaluates to <code>(+ 2 42)</code>.
But in, for example, an <code>and</code> statement, you only want the 2nd argument to be evaluated if the first argument is true.
Therefore it is not possible to implement an <code>and</code> statement, among others, as a function. <a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref" data-footnote-backref data-footnote-backref-idx="2" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn-3">
<p>Eventually I ran a brainfuck interpreter in my brainfuck interpreter in my lisp, and used that to run a brainfuck hello world program.
That one took around 24 hours to run. <a href="#fnref-3" class="footnote-backref" data-footnote-backref data-footnote-backref-idx="3" aria-label="Back to reference 3">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>