<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>JorisL blog</title><link>http://</link><description>My personal blog</description><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 12:10:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>marmite</generator><item><title>Skull rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-skull-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Skull."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-skull-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>The quintessence of bluffing.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/92415/skull">Skull</a> is a bluffing and deduction party-game, best played with 5 or 6 players.
The first player to with 2 bets, or the last player with any cards remaining, wins the game.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 4-6 (best 5-6)</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: 20 minutes</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<p>Each player gets 3 red-colored number cards, known as roses, and 1 black-colored face card (Jack, Queen, or King), known as skulls.</p>
<p>Choose a starting player.</p>
<h2><a href="#start-of-a-round" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="start-of-a-round"></a>Start of a round</h2>
<p>At the start of a round, each player chooses one of their cards an places it face-down in front of them.</p>
<h2><a href="#player-turns" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="player-turns"></a>Player turns</h2>
<p>On a players turn they can choose to either:</p>
<ul>
<li>Play a card. This card must be placed on top of any previous cards they played this round.</li>
<li>Make a bet.</li>
</ul>
<p>When a player makes a bet, they announce a number of cards they can reveal without encountering a skull.
After a player has made a bet, no one can play any other cards. They can only choose to pass or raise the bet.</p>
<p>Betting continues until all other players have passed; the highest bidder the attempts to reveal the declared number of cards.</p>
<h2><a href="#revealing-cards" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="revealing-cards"></a>Revealing cards</h2>
<p>The highest bidder must reveal cards.
They must first reveal cards from their own pile, after which they can reveal cards from the other players piles.
When revealing a card, the top most card of the chosen pile is revealed; earlier played cards in a pile can only be revealed by first revealing the cards above.</p>
<p>If the bidder reveals a skull they stop immediately.
If the skull is in their own pile, they take back all of their cards (not yet lost in a previous round), and choose 1 card to remove.
If the skull is in another players pile, they take back all of their cards, shuffle them with their hand cards, and let the player whose skull was encountered discard a card by random.
Cards are removed from the game face-down, e.g. only the person whose card it was knows which one was removed.</p>
<p>If the bidder was able to reveal the declared number of cards without encountering a skull they get 1 point.
Use a token (preferably a distinct object, but one of the non-used cards like Aces or Jokers also work) to show if a player has a point.</p>
<p>If the bidder wins the bid, they start the next round.
Otherwise the round is started by the player whose skull was revealed (can also be the bidder).</p>
<p>Unrevealed cards are returned to their owners hand, without revealing them to the other players.</p>
<h2><a href="#end-of-the-game" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="end-of-the-game"></a>End of the game</h2>
<p>Once a player acquires 2 points they win the game.
Otherwise, if a player is the only player left with any cards they also win the game.</p>
<h2><a href="#closing-words" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="closing-words"></a>Closing words</h2>
<p>See <a href="https://youtu.be/rK2locyo-Pc">this video</a> from Tom Scott for a nice gameplay example of this game.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Schnapsen rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-schnapsen-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Schnapsen."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-schnapsen-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>A 2-player trick taking game.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p>Schnapsen is a trick taking game for 2 players consisting of multiple rounds, where in each round players are racing to be the first to score 66 points.
Points during a round are awarded based on the card scores (face value for number cards, 11 points for aces) and for declaring a marriage, which is a 3 and 4 of the same suit.
Multiple rounds are placed until a player reached 7 points worth of rounds.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 2</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards (20 cards, using 2, 3, 4, 10, and Aces)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: 30 minutes</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#gameplay" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="gameplay"></a>Gameplay</h2>
<h3><a href="#round-setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="round-setup"></a>Round setup</h3>
<p>At the start of each round, both players are dealt 5 cards.
Use the 10 remaining cards to form the draw pile, and tuck 1 of these cards face-up underneath the other 9 cards.
The face-up card determines the trump suit this round.</p>
<h3><a href="#tricks" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="tricks"></a>Tricks</h3>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trick-taking_game">Tricks</a> are played using the following rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>The first trick in a round is lead by the non-dealer. Later tricks are lead by the winner of the last trick.</li>
<li>Highest card of the trump suit wins the trick.</li>
<li>If no trump is played; the highest card of the leading suit wins the trick.</li>
<li>Players do not have to follow suit.</li>
</ul>
<p>Once the draw pile is exhausted or <a href="#closing-the-draw-pile">closed</a> the following additional rules apply:</p>
<ul>
<li>Players must follow suit, and play a higher card in that suit if possible.</li>
<li>If players can't follow suit they must play a trump, if able.</li>
</ul>
<p>After a trick is played, both players draw a card from the draw pile into their hand.
The winner of the trick draws first and then the loser of the trick; e.g. when there's only 2 cards left the loser draws the face-up trump card.</p>
<p>Won tricks are kept face-down by its winner; neither player may look at those cards later during the round.</p>
<p>The lead player may, before playing a card, <a href="#exchanging-trump">exchange the trump</a>, <a href="#melding-a-marriage">meld a marriage</a>, and/or <a href="#closing-the-draw-pile">close the draw pile</a>.</p>
<h3><a href="#exchanging-trump" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="exchanging-trump"></a>Exchanging trump</h3>
<p>While the draw pile is not exhausted or closed, and the leading player has the 2 of the trump suit in hand, that player may exchange that card with the face-up card in the draw pile.
This exchange must be performed before starting the trick, and this exchange may be done at the start of the first trick.</p>
<h3><a href="#melding-a-marriage" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="melding-a-marriage"></a>Melding a marriage</h3>
<p>If the leading player has a 3 and 4 of the same suit in their hand, they can declare a marriage by showing both cards.
If these cards are from the trump suit that player scores 40 points, and 20 points if from another suit.
The player must then lead that trick using either of the 2 cards.</p>
<p>A marriage can be declared during any point in the round, but the points will only be given to that player if/when that player wins at least 1 trick that round.
E.g. if a player ends the round without any tricks won, than that player doesn't get any points from declared marriages.</p>
<h3><a href="#closing-the-draw-pile" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="closing-the-draw-pile"></a>Closing the draw pile</h3>
<p>If the leading player thinks they can reach the required 66 points using cards left in their hand, they may choose to, at the start of their turn, to close the draw pile by turning over the face-up trump card.
Once this has been done, neither player draws any cards at the end of a trick, and the stricter rules apply for playing cards in a trick.</p>
<p>When the draw pile is closed, the non-closing player counts and records their current score.</p>
<h3><a href="#ending-the-round" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="ending-the-round"></a>Ending the round</h3>
<p>The round ends when neither player has cards left to play.
Scoring is dependent on if the draw pile was closed during the game.</p>
<p>If the game was played without closing the draw pile, then the winner of the last trick wins the round, with the round being worth 1 point.</p>
<p>If the draw pile was closed, and the person who closed the draw pile has 66 or more points, then that player wins the round.
The round is worth points dependent on the score of the other player once the draw pile was closed.</p>
<ul>
<li>3 points if the non-closing player had 0 points.</li>
<li>2 points if the non-closing player had 32 points or less.</li>
<li>1 point if the non-closing player had 33 points or more.</li>
</ul>
<p>If the player who closed the draw pile is not able to reach 66 points, the non-closing player wins the round:
If so, the round is worth:</p>
<ul>
<li>3 points if the non-closing player had 0 points when the draw pile was closed.</li>
<li>2 points otherwise.</li>
</ul>
<p>Play continues until a player scores at least 7 points worth of rounds.</p>
<p>#$ Closing words</p>
<p>Schnapsen is traditionally played with Jack, Queen, King replacing the 2, 3, 4 cards respectively.
Using this convention the concept of marriages are easier to understand, since this then happens with a trick consisting of a King and Queen.
However, the card score values are more difficult to grasp, especially since the point values and ranking order for the face cards differ from most conventional card games.
Therefore I like to teach and play this game using 2, 3, and 4 instead.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sixty-six_(card_game)">Sixty-six</a> is a card game almost similar to Schnapsen.
The main differences are that the 9's are also included, worth 0 points, and that each player has a hand of 6 instead of 5 cards.
When playing Sixty-six, it is likely easier to use the standard convention of Jack, Queen, and King cards, since with the 9 included, cards are not worth their face-value anyway.
(or the face-card convention can be used, with the Jack included as the 0 card).</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Whist rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-whist-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Whist."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-whist-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>A 2-player trick taking game.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p>Whist is a 2-player trick taking game played in 2 phases.
During the first phase the players try to win tricks in order to draft the cards that weren't dealt at the start of the game.
During the second phase the players try to win the most tricks.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 2</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards (52 cards, without jokers)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: 15 minutes</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<p>Decide which player will start the game.
Shuffle all cards, and deal 13 to each player.
Place the remaining 26 cards face down as the stock, and flip over the top most card.
The suit of this card is the trump suit for the remainder of the game.</p>
<h2><a href="#phase-1-drafting" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="phase-1-drafting"></a>Phase 1: drafting</h2>
<p>During the first half of the game, the players try to draft the best cards from the stock.</p>
<p>Standard trick-taking rules apply:</p>
<ul>
<li>The leading player plays a card from their hand.</li>
<li>The other player must follow suit, if possible. Otherwise they may play any card from their hand.</li>
<li>The winner of the trick is determined by:
<ul>
<li>The highest card of the trump suit.</li>
<li>If no trump suit is played; the highest card of the leading suit.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The winner of the trick leads the next trick.</li>
</ul>
<p>The person who won the trick gets the top (open) card of the stock.
The other person gets the card below, without showing it to the other player.
Cards received during this phase directly get added to the players hand, and can be used in either phase.
The top card of the stock is revealed for the next trick.</p>
<p>Play continues until the stock is depleted.
All cards played in tricks during this phase are set aside.</p>
<h2><a href="#phase-2-scoring" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="phase-2-scoring"></a>Phase 2: scoring</h2>
<p>During this phase the players continue playing tricks until their hands are depleted (13 tricks in total).
The winner of the game is the player who scored the most tricks during this phase of play.</p>
<h2><a href="#closing-words" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="closing-words"></a>Closing words</h2>
<p><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/233961/claim">Claim</a> is a modern designer card game with gameplay similar to Whist; 2-player trick taking with a drafting and scoring phase.</p>
<p><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/221965/the-fox-in-the-forest">Fox in the Forest</a> is another enjoyable modern designer 2-player trick taking game.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Pixies solo rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-pixies-solo-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Solo rules for the card game Pixies."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>solitaire</category><guid>http:///gamerules-pixies-solo-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<h1><a href="#pixies-solo-rules" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="pixies-solo-rules"></a>Pixies Solo Rules</h1>
<p><em>These rules are based on the <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/thread/3282756/2024-solomode-breeze">Breeze solo mode by Michiel de Wit</a>.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p>In this solo mode, you play a 2-player game against a bot.
As normal, 3 rounds are played, each with different scoring for connected zones.
The bot doesn't make a 3x3 area, but gathers cards in a single pile, with its own scoring rules.</p>
<p>From the players perspective, the round sequence is the same as for a normal 2 player game,
except for the 4 cards being drafted must be put from left-to-right when revealed.</p>
<p>A round ends when the player has no open slots left over.</p>
<h2><a href="#bot-turn" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="bot-turn"></a>Bot turn</h2>
<p>During the bot's turn:</p>
<ol>
<li>Take the card with the highest number from the drafting pool, with the leftmost card winning ties.</li>
<li>If there are still 2 or 3 cards left in the drafting pool, put the taken card face up on the bot's pile.
Otherwise discard the card face-down in a discard pile.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a href="#bot-scoring" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="bot-scoring"></a>Bot scoring</h2>
<p>Go through the bot's (face up) pile, and calculate the score as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Add up all card values, as if all cards where validated.</li>
<li>Add up all positive and negative points printed on the cards as normal.</li>
<li>See what color the bot has most (taking multi-colored cards into account),
and calculate the largest color zone (2, 3, or 4 points per card, depending on round) as if these cards where all connected.</li>
</ul>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Loot the Loop rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-loot-the-loop-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Loot the Loop."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>solitaire</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-loot-the-loop-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>Rules taken from the <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/thread/2587399/isaludo-ten-new-solo-card-games-playable-with-a-st">Isaludo solo collection</a></em></p>
<h2><a href="#components" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="components"></a>Components</h2>
<ul>
<li>A standard 52-card deck with one joker.</li>
<li>Aces are <strong>jewels</strong> you're trying to loot. Number cards (2-10) are minor <strong>trinkets</strong> in the temple. Face cards are <strong>traps</strong> you must avoid, while the Joker is the temple <strong>exit</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<ol>
<li>Cut the deck in 3 equal face-down piles, flip over the top 2 cards for each pile, and stack the piles back in your chosen order. Hold this deck in your hand.</li>
<li>Leave space on the table for 3 cards (your <strong>notes</strong>) and a <strong>score pile</strong>.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a href="#gameplay" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="gameplay"></a>Gameplay</h2>
<p>The game is played over a series of turns. Each turn, you must perform <strong>exactly one</strong> of the following four actions. What actions are allowed depends on the top or top two cards of the deck.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Action</th>
<th>Can only be performed if...</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Look Around</td>
<td>The top card of the deck is face down</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Explore</td>
<td>Either or both of the top two cards in the deck are face-up number cards (trinkets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mark a path</td>
<td>The top card of the deck is a face up number card (trinket), and you have less than three cards in your notes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Return to a marked path</td>
<td>You have at least one marked path in your notes</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3><a href="#look-around" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="look-around"></a>Look Around</h3>
<p>Turn the <strong>top two cards</strong> of the deck face up, careful to maintain their order.
If the second card of the deck is already face up, just flip the top card and leave the second one as is.</p>
<p>You may ONLY perform this action if the top card of the deck is face down.</p>
<h3><a href="#explore" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="explore"></a>Explore</h3>
<p>If either or both of the top two cards in the deck are face-up number cards (trinkets), choose one of those cards' values.
Count exactly that many cards from the top of the deck and move them to the bottom, maintaining their order.
Include the aforementioned top two cards in the count.</p>
<p>If there is only one face-up number card among the top two cards of the deck, you may only travel by that count.
If neither of the two top cards of the deck are face up number cards, you may not use the explore action at all.</p>
<p>Each time you explore, after you move the required cards to the back, take note of the new top card of your deck.
This is the room you land in.</p>
<ul>
<li>If it is a <strong>face-down card</strong>, nothing happens.</li>
<li>If it is a <strong>face-up face card</strong> (trap), you lose the game.</li>
<li>If it is a <strong>face-up ace</strong> (jewel) or trinket (number card), you nab it! You must move that card to your score pile.</li>
<li>If it is a <strong>face-up joker</strong> (exit) and you have all four aces in your score pile, you exit the temple and end the game. Otherwise, nothing happens.</li>
</ul>
<h3><a href="#mark-a-path" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="mark-a-path"></a>Mark a Path</h3>
<p>If the top card of the deck is a number card (trinket), remove that card from the deck and place that card face up in front of you on the table in your notes.
You can mark a maximum of <strong>three</strong> paths at any one time.</p>
<p>Remember that treasures you land on are removed from the temple, so the longer you stay the greater the density of traps!</p>
<h3><a href="#return-to-a-previously-marked-path" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="return-to-a-previously-marked-path"></a>Return to a Previously Marked Path</h3>
<p>Return a path card of your choice from your notes to the top of the deck, face up.</p>
<p>Marking paths and returning to paths changes the top cards of your deck, and is the primary way to manipulate movement options when trying to land on specific cards.</p>
<p>Remember that marking and returning are separate actions.
If your notes are already full, you can't &quot;swap&quot; a saved note and the top card of the deck.</p>
<h2><a href="#game-end" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="game-end"></a>Game End</h2>
<p>Continue exploring the temple and hunting for the jewels (aces) and exit (joker).
If you get stuck in the temple and can't move, or all movement choices you have will land you on a trap, you lose the game.</p>
<p><strong>If you land on the face-up exit</strong> after an explore action, check your score pile.
<strong>If you already have all four jewels</strong>, you immediately escape the temple and win the game.</p>
<p>Your score is the total number of cards in your score pile, including trinkets.</p>
<h2><a href="#other-notes" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="other-notes"></a>Other notes</h2>
<ul>
<li>Even with all aces and joker face-up, it can be interesting to stay in the temple to gather more trinkets.</li>
<li>You are free to look through the deck and all its face up cards at any time. You may even count cards to plan routes. You may not look at any face down cards, however.</li>
<li>When traveling, it’s helpful to first count off the total number of cards to move with your thumb, then transfer the whole block of cards to the back. It's easier than doing it one by one.</li>
</ul>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Sea Salt &amp; Paper solo rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-sea-salt-paper-solo-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Solo rules for the card game Sea Salt & Paper."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>solitaire</category><guid>http:///gamerules-sea-salt-paper-solo-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<h1><a href="#sea-salt--paper-solo-rules" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="sea-salt--paper-solo-rules"></a>Sea Salt &amp; Paper Solo Rules</h1>
<p><em>These rules are based on the <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/thread/3382394/dumb-ai-solo-version">solo rules by @EricKenneth</a>.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p>In this solo mode, you play a 2-player game against a bot.
This game consists of a single round, where you can stop the round once you reach 12 points.
The bot's actions are determined by a d6 dice, and this dice also limits the actions on your turn.
The bot does not play cards, but gathers them in a face-down pile. It's score is determined using special scoring rules.</p>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<ol>
<li>Place a mermaid card sideways representing the bot. Its cards will be placed right below it.</li>
<li>Place a d6 on the mermaid area for now.</li>
<li>Place the deck and the two discards as usual to the right of the mermaid's area.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a href="#special-rules" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="special-rules"></a>Special rules</h2>
<ul>
<li>The player always starts the game.</li>
<li>Whenever a discard pile is empty, immediately fill it with the top card of the deck.</li>
<li>The player can't choose to draw from a pile if the dice is on that pile (taking a card from that pile using the crab action is allowed).</li>
<li>When playing the swimmer-shark combo, shuffle the bot's pile and take a random card.</li>
<li>When playing the swimmer-jellyfish combo, the bot takes the top card from the draw pile in its turn. The dice does not change position.</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#bots-turn" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="bots-turn"></a>Bot's turn</h2>
<p>During the bot's turn:</p>
<ol>
<li>Roll the dice, and put the top card from the corresponding pile face down on the bot's pile.
<ul>
<li>1 or 2: deck.</li>
<li>3 or 4: first discard pile.</li>
<li>5 or 6: second discard pile.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Place the dice on the pile the card was taken from.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a href="#ending-the-game" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="ending-the-game"></a>Ending the game</h2>
<p>Once the player reaches 12 points, they can choose to end the game.
Then take a final turn for the bot.</p>
<h2><a href="#scoring" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="scoring"></a>Scoring</h2>
<p>Scoring for the player is according to the standard rules (without last-chance scoring).</p>
<p>To count the bot's score:</p>
<ol>
<li>Make as many duo-card pairs as possible, adding sea stars if possible.</li>
<li>Count score using the standard rules, also including the mermaid card representing the bot.</li>
<li>Add 1 point for every single duo-card.</li>
</ol>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Gridcannon rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-gridcannon-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Gridcannon."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>solitaire</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-gridcannon-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>Rules taken from <a href="https://www.pentadact.com/2019-08-20-gridcannon-a-single-player-game-with-regular-playing-cards/#Update">here</a></em></p>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<ol>
<li>Start with a shuffled deck, including jokers.</li>
<li>With the deck face-down, draw cards from the top and lay them out face-up in a 3×3 grid. If you draw any royals, aces or jokers during this, put them on a separate pile and keep drawing til you have made the grid of just number cards.</li>
<li>If you did draw some royals, you now place them the same way we will when playing: put it outside the grid, adjacent to the grid card it is most similar to. ‘Most similar’ means:
<ol>
<li>Highest value card of the same suit</li>
<li>If none, highest value card of the same color</li>
<li>If none, highest value card</li>
<li>If there is a tie, or most similar card is on a corner, you can choose between the equally valid positions</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Any aces and jokers you drew during set up, keep them face-up to one side. These are Ploys you can play whenever you like, rules below.</li>
<li>Once you have a 3×3 grid of number cards, you may choose one to replace if you like: put it on the bottom of the draw pile and draw a new card to replace it.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a href="#the-goal" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="the-goal"></a>The goal</h2>
<p>Find and kill all the royals.</p>
<h2><a href="#play" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="play"></a>Play</h2>
<p>Draw the top card from the deck.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>If it is a royal:</strong> use placement rule above.</li>
<li><strong>If it has value 2-10:</strong> you must place it on the grid. It can go on any card with the same or lower value, regardless of suit.</li>
<li><strong>If it is an ace or joker:</strong> keep it to one side, see <strong>Ploys</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Killing royals:</strong> if you are able to place a card on the grid opposite a royal – so there are two cards between – those two cards <strong>Attack</strong> the royal.
The sum of their values must be at least as much as health of the royal to kill them:
if it is not, you can still place the card, but the royal is unaffected.
The value of the card you just placed is not part of the Attack, only the two between.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Jacks:</strong> 11 health. The cards Attacking can be any suit.</li>
<li><strong>Queens:</strong> 12 health. The cards Attacking must match the color of the queen to count.</li>
<li><strong>Kings:</strong> 13 health. The cards Attacking must match the suit of the king to count.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you killed the royal, turn it face down but don't remove it – new royals you draw still cannot be placed in that spot.
Once every spot around the grid has a dead royal in it (12 total) you have won.</p>
<p><strong>Ploys:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aces are Extractions:</strong> at any time you can use up one of the aces you have drawn to pick up one stack of cards from the grid and put them face-down at the bottom of your draw pile. You can do this even after drawing a card and before placing it. Turn the ace face-down to remember you have used it.</li>
<li><strong>Jokers are Reassignments:</strong> at any time you can use up one you have drawn to move the top card of one stack on the grid to another position. The place you move it to must be a valid spot to play the card, and placing it can trigger an Attack the same way a normal play can. Turn the joker face-down to remember you have used it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If you cannot place a card:</strong> and you have no Ploys to use, you must add the card as <strong>Armour</strong> to the royal it is most similar to (lowest value royal of same suit, failing that lowest of same color, etc). It increases their health by the value of the card. So a King with a 3 as armor now has 13 + 3 = 16 health. You can add armor to a royal that already has armor – it stacks. If a royal ends up with 20+ health (or 19+ for a King), that is a natural loss as there is no longer any way to kill them.</p>
<p><strong>If there are no living royals on the table:</strong> if every spot around the grid has a dead royal on it – all 12 – you have won! If not, just keep drawing cards until you find a royal, placing the cards in a face-up pile as you go. Once you find a royal, place it, then add the cards you cycled through to the bottom of your deck.</p>
<p><strong>If the draw pile runs out:</strong> and you have not killed all the royals, use any ploys you have left to fix the situation if you can. If you are out of both cards and ploys and not all royals are dead, you have lost.</p>
<h2><a href="#scoring" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="scoring"></a>Scoring</h2>
<p>If you have killed all the royals without running out of cards, your score is how many Ploys you have left unspent.
So the maximum score is 6.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Le Truc rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-le-truc-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Le Truc."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-le-truc-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<h1><a href="#le-truc" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="le-truc"></a>Le Truc</h1>
<p><em>A bluffing &amp; trick taking game with only 3 cards per hand.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p>Le Truc is a small bluffing &amp; trick taking game where players (or teams) race to 16 points.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 2 or 4.</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards, only 32 cards (remove all 2-6 and joker cards). Cards are ranked (high to low): A-K-Q-J-10-9-8-7.</li>
<li>Something to keep score (pen &amp; paper, chips, coins, etc.)</li>
<li>Optional: backgammon doubling cube.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: 20 minutes.</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#gameplay" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="gameplay"></a>Gameplay</h2>
<p>At the start of each round the dealer deals 3 cards to each player.
The leader of the first trick is the player left of the dealer.
The leader of the first trick may propose, after cards have been dealt, a re-deal.
If the dealer agrees the hand is re-dealt.</p>
<p>Each trick, the leader plays a card, with the other players following in clockwise order.
Unlike most trick taking games, Le Truc is suit-less.
Therefore a player can play any card and the highest card wins, irregardless of suit.
The winner of a trick starts the next trick.</p>
<p>Before playing a card, that player can increase the bet, see <a href="betting.html" data-wikilink="true">Betting</a> below.
This may be done before playing their first card.</p>
<p>If the highest cards are tied, no one wins the trick.</p>
<p>A player or team wins the round when they win the majority of tricks.
If a player or team wins the first 2 tricks, the 3rd trick is not played out, and all remaining cards are shuffled back into the deck without reveal to the other players.
If both players or teams win the same number of tricks, then no points are scored this round.</p>
<h2><a href="#betting" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="betting"></a>Betting</h2>
<p>By default, each round is worth 1 point.</p>
<p>Before a player plays their card they are allowed to double the current value of the round.
If the other player or team accept the point value of the round is doubled (e.g. 2, 4, 8, 16).
If the other player or team declines, the player offering to double scores the current game worth, and the round ends immediately (returning all left over cards to the deck without reveal).</p>
<p>Once a bet has been accepted in a round, only the player or team who accepted the last bet that round can offer to double again.</p>
<p>Note: these betting rules are similar to those from the doubling cube in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backgammon">Backgammon</a>.</p>
<h2><a href="#team-play" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="team-play"></a>Team play</h2>
<p>When playing in teams, the partners sit opposite of each other.</p>
<p>Open communication between team members is allowed, as long as it can also be heard by the opposing team.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Nine Card Golf rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-nine-card-golf-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Nine Card Golf."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-nine-card-golf-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<h1><a href="#nine-card-golf" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="nine-card-golf"></a>Nine Card Golf</h1>
<p><em>Players draw and discard to minimize the total value of their tableau of 9 cards.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p>The game is played over 4 rounds, where in each round each player tries to get as few points as possible.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 2+</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards (52 cards + 2 jokers) per 2-3 players</li>
<li>Something to keep the running score for each player</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: 15-20 minutes</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<p>Shuffle all cards (including jokers) and deal out 9 cards face down to each player.
Players arrange their cards in a 3x3 grid, keeping the cards face down.</p>
<p>Place the remaining cards as a draw pile in the center of the table, and flip over 1 card to start the discard pile.</p>
<p>Choose a player to start the first round.
On subsequent rounds, the player who scored the most points in the prior round is the starting player.</p>
<p>Each player flips over 3 cars of their choosing in their grid, without looking at the other cards.</p>
<h2><a href="#actions" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="actions"></a>Actions</h2>
<p>A player chooses one of the following actions in their turn:</p>
<ol>
<li>Draw and look at the top card of the draw pile. The player then chooses either to:
<ol>
<li>Replacing one of their grid cards with the drawn card, discarding the replaced card.</li>
<li>Discarding the drawn card, after which the player may choose to flip one of the face-down cards in their grid.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Replace one of their grid cards with the top card of the discard pile, discarding the replaced card.</li>
</ol>
<p>Either a face-down or face-up card can be replaced, but the new card is always played face-up.
Discarded cards are always placed face-up on top of the discard pile.</p>
<p>When a player reveals all cards in their grid, all other players get 1 additional turn, after which the round is scored.</p>
<h2><a href="#scoring" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="scoring"></a>Scoring</h2>
<p>Each player first flips over their face-down cards, if still remaining.
Then each player scores using the following rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Aces are worth 1 point.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Numbered cards (2-10) are worth their face-value.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Jacks and Queens are worth 10 points.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Kings are worth 0 points.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Jokers are worth -2 points.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If a card is orthogonal adjacent with a card of the same value, it scores 0 points instead.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A set of 4 same-valued cards in a 2x2 block score -10 points.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If the player who ended the round (first to reveal all cards in their grid) did not get the lowest score this round, they get a +10 point penalty.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Players keep a running count of their scores over multiple rounds.
The player with the lowest total score wins.</p>
<h2><a href="#closing-words" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="closing-words"></a>Closing words</h2>
<p>As with most classic card games, there are many variants of the card game Golf, see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golf_(card_game)">Wikipedia</a>.
Nine-card golf, using rules as explained on this page, is my preferred way to play.</p>
<p>In my opinion this game works bests as a 2-player game, because of:</p>
<ul>
<li>The speed of play.</li>
<li>High importance to not only care for your own grid, but also to prevent throwing away cards the opponent can use.</li>
<li>The use of a single-card deck causes fewer opportunities making sets of cards, leading to more strategic decisions and less chance.</li>
</ul>
<p>The game <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/204135/skyjo">Skyjo</a> is a modern implementation of the Golf family of card games, suitable for 2-5 players.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Emissary rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-the-emissary-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game The Emissary."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>solitaire</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-the-emissary-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>Rules taken from the <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/thread/2587399/isaludo-ten-new-solo-card-games-playable-with-a-st">Isaludo solo collection</a>. This game holds the core of the game <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/334590/for-northwood-a-solo-trick-taking-game">For Northwood</a>.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#components" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="components"></a>Components</h2>
<ul>
<li>A standard 52-card deck without jokers.</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<p>Separate the 9s and 10s (<strong>kingdoms</strong>) and place these eight cards face down in a row (they're just placeholders; the value doesn't matter).
Separate the twelve face cards.
Shuffle the Kings and Queens together (<strong>rulers</strong>) and deal them face up from left to right, one on top of each kingdom.</p>
<p>Set the four Jacks aside in a stack; these cards represent you and your <strong>advisors</strong>.
Shuffle the remaining 32 cards into a face-down <strong>deck</strong>.</p>
<h2><a href="#objective" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="objective"></a>Objective</h2>
<p>In <em>The Emissary</em>, you are a young noble sent by your father to gather support from eight neighboring kingdoms.
In each kingdom, you engage in a series of debates with their ruler.
Using the right amount of force and deference, you must win exactly a certain number of debates per kingdom.
Succeed and you may call upon the ruler for future support; fail even once and lose the game.</p>
<h2><a href="#gameplay" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="gameplay"></a>Gameplay</h2>
<p>The core game loop consists of 1) visiting a kingdom and 2) playing out a series of debates in that kingdom against its ruler.</p>
<h2><a href="#choosing-the-kingdom-to-visit" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="choosing-the-kingdom-to-visit"></a>Choosing the kingdom to visit</h2>
<p>Draw eight cards from the deck.
Review the cards in your hand, then choose which kingdom to visit.
Place your stack of advisors under that kingdom to mark that you're visiting.
You must visit each kingdom once and only once per game.</p>
<p>The position of that kingdom along the line determines how many debates you must <strong>exactly</strong> win to get support from that ruler.
The leftmost royal needs one win, the next two, and so on.
You must win eight debates in the rightmost kingdom.</p>
<p>The ruler's suit represents their favorite topic; for this kingdom, this suit <strong>trumps</strong> all other topics of conversation.</p>
<p>Once you have chosen a kingdom to visit, you now play out the series of debates.</p>
<h2><a href="#the-debates" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="the-debates"></a>The Debates</h2>
<p>Place the top card of the draw deck face-up into a discard pile.
The ruler is now talking about a topic - you must respond!
Play a single card from your hand in response.
Playing a card follows standard trick-taking rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>You must play a card in your hand with the same suit (topic) as the ruler's card if you are able.</li>
<li>If and only if you cannot follow suit, you may play any card.</li>
</ul>
<p>You win the debate if either:</p>
<ul>
<li>You played a higher card of the same topic (suit), or</li>
<li>The debate card isn't of the ruler's favorite topic and you responded with any card of their favorite topic. Way to go, you suckup.</li>
</ul>
<p>Aces are low and have value 1.
If you win the debate, place the card you played in a separate scoring pile.
If you lose the debate, instead place your card in the discard pile as well.
Keep engaging in debates until you run out of cards in your hand.
Once your hand is empty, the number of cards in your scoring pile shows how many debates you have won for that kingdom.</p>
<h2><a href="#advisor-abilities" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="advisor-abilities"></a>Advisor Abilities</h2>
<p>To help control the number of debates you win, each of your Jack advisors has a special ability you can activate, once per kingdom.
<strong>Before the first debate or between any two debates</strong>, you may choose to activate advisor abilities by turning a face-up Jack face down.
(Activate it before the ruler card is dealt; you can't use abilities 'in response').</p>
<p>It's up to you whether you want to use abilities earlier when you have more cards in hand, toward the end, or a mix of both.
Resolve each ability fully before deciding to use another one.</p>
<p>The ability depends on the suit of the card used:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hearts</strong> (diplomacy) - Discard all cards in your hand that match the current kingdom's trump suit.</li>
<li><strong>Clubs</strong> (military) - Draw a card for each club in your hand.</li>
<li><strong>Spades</strong> (politics) - Swap the current ruler with the ruler of an unvisited kingdom. (This changes the trump suit for all debates of this kingdom moving forward, and also for that other kingdom when you visit it). This ability does nothing when you're visiting the final kingdom.</li>
<li><strong>Diamonds</strong> (commerce) - Draw two cards, then choose and discard two cards from your hand.</li>
</ul>
<p>Hearts and clubs abilities change the number of cards in your hand, and therefore change the total number of debates you need to play in a kingdom.
The target win number remains the same, however.</p>
<p>If you run out of cards in the draw pile, shuffle the discard pile and continue using it.</p>
<p>When you run out of cards in your hand, if you have won exactly the number of debates equal to the kingdom's number, congratulations!
Add that ruler face up beneath your advisors.
In future kingdoms, you may also turn a supporting <strong>king or queen face down</strong> to use their suit's ability.
The only difference is that unlike Jacks whose abilities you can use once per kingdom, kings
and queens are <strong>one-time-use</strong> abilities.
They're still very useful in a pinch, though.</p>
<p>Shuffle all the cards in the discard, scoring pile, and draw deck together.
Turn all spent Jacks back face up (not kings and queens), draw eight new cards, and choose the next kingdom to visit.</p>
<h2><a href="#ending-the-game" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="ending-the-game"></a>Ending the game</h2>
<p>Continue visiting the kingdoms one by one, convincing (and leveraging) allies as needed.
If you end any kingdom without winning the exact number of debates needed, you <strong>lose the game</strong>.</p>
<p>Note that the central kingdoms are slightly easier, with kingdom 1 and 8 being very hard to win.
Grab support before attempting these, and approach them when you're dealt a favorable hand!</p>
<p>If you <strong>get support from all eight kingdoms</strong>, you win the game.
Whether you win or lose, your score is the number of kingdoms won plus the number of supporting kings/queens with unused abilities, for a perfect score of 8+8=16 points.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Ricochet Poker rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-ricochet-poker-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Ricochet Poker."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-ricochet-poker-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>Poker without bluffing.</em></p>
<h1><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h1>
<p>Ricochet poker is a form of poker without bluffing, and with an emphasis on calculating odds and pressing luck.
During a round, all players ante an then receive a portion of their poker hand.
The player with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_poker_hands">lowest poker hand</a> either chooses to buy more cards or fold.
The player with the best hand at the end of the round wins the pot.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 3-6</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards (52 cards, without jokers), ranked aces-high.</li>
<li>Chips, coins, etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: ?</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<p>Each round starts with all players making an ante of 1 chip.
Then each player receives 1 card, face up.</p>
<p>The person with the lowest poker hand hand (e.g. lowest card at the start of the round) acts first.
Suits are ranked in alphabetical order, from low to high: Clubs, Diamonds, Hearts, Spades.</p>
<h2><a href="#gameplay" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="gameplay"></a>Gameplay</h2>
<p>On a players turn, they either fold or buy cards.</p>
<p>If a player folds, they step out of the round.</p>
<p>If a player buys cards, they first announce how many they want to buy, and put that many chips in the pot.
Players may only buy cards up to a total hand size of 5 cards.
The dealer will give the cards, face-up, stopping directly when the hand is not the lowest hand anymore.
Note: it can be that the player therefore received fewer cards than bought for.</p>
<p>If a player buys cards and still has the lowest poker hand after receiving their bought cards, that player is out of the round.</p>
<p>After every turn the action moves to the player with the lowest hand.</p>
<p>Play continues until there's 1 player left, or if there is a tie for the best hand.</p>
<h3><a href="#breaking-ties" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="breaking-ties"></a>Breaking ties</h3>
<p>A hand with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kicker_(poker)">kicker</a> beats a hand without (for example, a King+3 hand beats a hand of a single King, but a King+8 beats a King+3).
Suits are used to break ties given identical hands.
In the final hand, suits are not used to break ties; only to determine the next player in turn.
If at the end of a round 2 or more players are tied, the pot is split.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Bourré rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-bourre-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Nine Card Golf."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-bourre-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<h1><a href="#bourré" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="bourré"></a>Bourré</h1>
<p><em>A trick taking gambling game.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p>Players try to win more tricks than any other single player to win the pot, and try to win at least 1 trick to not match the pot.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 3-8 (best with 5-7)</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards (52 cards, without jokers), ranked aces-high.</li>
<li>Chips, coins, etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: ?</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<p>Each player antes 1 chip in the pot, and is dealt 5 cards.
The last card dealt to the dealer is flipped open and placed in front of the dealer; this is the trump suite this round.</p>
<p>Starting left from the dealer, each player decides if they stay in or fold.
If a player folds, they place their hand cards face-down in front of them.
They cannot longer win the pot on that deal, nor lose any additional chips.
If a player stays, they can decide to discard up to 5 cards face down (up to 3 when playing with 7 or 8) and drawing that amount of cards from the unused portion of the deck.</p>
<p>Players may not announce or gesture indicating whether they intend to play or not or how many cards they might exchange, before it is their turn to act.</p>
<p>If there are no more cards remaining in the deck to exchange cards, the dealer gathers all discarded cards and shuffles them to form the new deck.</p>
<p>If the flipped card is an ace, the dealer must play.</p>
<p>The dealer is allowed to exchange their flipped over card. If so, set this card aside face-up. This card still determines the trump suit.</p>
<p>If only 1 player elects to stay, that player is deemed to have won all tricks that round.</p>
<p>The player left of the dealer starts the first trick.
In subsequent rounds, the trick is started by the player who won the previous trick.</p>
<h2><a href="#trick-taking" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="trick-taking"></a>Trick taking</h2>
<p>The leading player plays a card, after which the other players play a card in clockwise order.
The trick is won by whoever played the highest card of the trump suit, or if none of the trump suit was played the highest card of the leading suit.</p>
<p>The play of cards are governed by these rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>Players must follow suit, if able.</li>
<li>Players not able to follow suit must play a trump card, if able.</li>
<li>Subject to the previous rules; a player must play a card that would, currently, win the trick, if able.</li>
<li>If a player neither has cards of the leading suit nor trump suit, they may play any card from their hand.</li>
</ul>
<p>Note: these rules have more restrictions than most trick-taking games.</p>
<p>If a player is not able to play a card that would win them the trick they may choose themselves which card to play, given the rules to play the lead suit or trump suit if not able.</p>
<p>The dealer's flipped over card is treated as one of their 5 hand cards and can be played at any time, given the rules stated above.</p>
<p>A player who is sure to win 3 tricks irrespective of how the cards are played, and therefore is certain to win the pot, has the following additional restrictions.</p>
<ul>
<li>If it is their turn to lead, they must lead with their highest trump.</li>
<li>If they are playing in a trick lead by another player, and not being the last one to play in that trick, they must play there highest trump if able (if allowed by the standard rules stated above).</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#payments" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="payments"></a>Payments</h2>
<p>The player who wins the most tricks wins the pot.
If multiple players are tied for the most tricks then no one takes the pot - it remains for the next deal and the new antes and penalties are added to it.</p>
<p>Any player who takes no trick is said to have gone &quot;bourré&quot;. These players must each pay an amount equal to the whole contents of the pot.
These payments form part of the pot for the next deal.</p>
<p>Players who have gone bourré and players who were tied for the most tricks do not pay an ante for the next deal.
All other players pay 1 chip ante as usual.
These payments are regardless of whether the player continues play in the next round.</p>
<p>Deal then passes to the left.</p>
<p>If a player plays a card not in accordance to the rules, and this is not fixed before the next player played their card, that player must forfeit the round and pay as if they have gone bourré at the end of the round.</p>
<h2><a href="#closing-words" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="closing-words"></a>Closing words</h2>
<p>Due to the quickly growing payments round after round, it can be prefferable to pay with a limit, for example 20 chips.
When played with a chip limit, players pay at most that limit when going bourré and the winner can only get that amount out of the pot (keeping the remainder of the pot for the next round).</p>
<p>See <a href="https://youtu.be/jQxpKAtvdT0">this</a> video from Shut Up &amp; Sit Down for a short explenation and playtrough of this game.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Coup rules</title><link>http:///gamerules-coup-rules.html</link><description><![CDATA["Rules for the card game Coup."]]></description><category>rules</category><category>standard 52-card deck</category><guid>http:///gamerules-coup-rules.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="http://">tag-rules</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown header -->
<p><em>A game of social deduction, bluffing, and deception.</em></p>
<h2><a href="#overview" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="overview"></a>Overview</h2>
<p><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/131357/coup">Coup</a> is a social deduction bluffing game, best played with 4 to 6 players.</p>
<p>A player wins if they are the last person with any cards remaining.
This game is intended to be played multiple times.</p>
<ul>
<li>Players: 3-6 (best 4-6), with variant for 2 players.</li>
<li>Prerequisites:
<ul>
<li>1 deck of cards</li>
<li>Optional: coins (tokens, chips, etc.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play time: 5-10 minutes per round</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#setup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="setup"></a>Setup</h2>
<p>Make a deck out of 3 of each of the following cards: Jack, Queen, King, Ace, 2.</p>
<p>Shuffle the deck, and deal 2 cards to each player.</p>
<p>The remaining cards are used as coins, if no other kind of tokens are available.
Give each player 2 starting coins.</p>
<h2><a href="#the-cards" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="the-cards"></a>The cards</h2>
<p>There are 5 kinds of character cards, each with their own ability.</p>
<h3><a href="#king--duke" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="king--duke"></a>King = Duke</h3>
<p>Take 3 coins.
Blocks foreign aid.</p>
<h3><a href="#ace--assassin" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="ace--assassin"></a>Ace = Assassin</h3>
<p>Pay 3 coins and try to assassinate another players character.
Can be blocked by a Contessa.</p>
<h3><a href="#queen--contessa" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="queen--contessa"></a>Queen = Contessa</h3>
<p>Blocks an assassination attempt against yourself.</p>
<h3><a href="#jack--captain" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="jack--captain"></a>Jack = Captain</h3>
<p>Steal 2 coins from another player.
Can be blocked by a Captain or Inquisitor.
Blocks stealing.</p>
<h3><a href="#2--inquisitor" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="2--inquisitor"></a>2 = Inquisitor</h3>
<p>Draw one card from the deck, and choose whether or not to exchange it with one of your cards.
Shuffle the drawn or exchanged card back into the deck.</p>
<p>-OR-</p>
<p>Choose a player to reveal one of their cards to you (their choice of which to show).
You may force that player to draw a new card and shuffle the revealed card back into the deck.</p>
<p>Inquisitor can block stealing.</p>
<h2><a href="#gameplay" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="gameplay"></a>Gameplay</h2>
<p>During a players turn they can use one of the following actions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Influence: use the ability of one of the character cards.</li>
<li>Income: take 1 coin from the pool.</li>
<li>Foreign aid: take 2 coins from the pool. Can be blocked by a Duke.</li>
<li>Coup: pay 7 coins back to the pool, and choose a player. That player removes one of their cards from their hand. Players are forced to coup if they have 10+ coins.</li>
</ul>
<p>If a player looses a card, either due to coup, assassination, or a bluff call, they place that card face-open in the middle of the table.</p>
<p>If a player doesn't have any cards left, they are out of the game for the remainder of the round.</p>
<h3><a href="#bluffing--deception" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="bluffing--deception"></a>Bluffing &amp; deception</h3>
<p>When a player uses a cards ability, either in their own turn, or as a reaction in someone else's turn, they are not required to have the claimed character; they can bluff that they have that character.</p>
<p>Any time a player uses a cards ability, any other player can challenge them.
If a player is challenged, they must reveal one of their cards.</p>
<ul>
<li>If the challenged player reveals the claimed card, the player who called on their bluff loses one of their cards. The challenged player shuffles the revealed card back into the deck and draws a new card.</li>
<li>If the challenged player reveals another card, that player looses the revealed card.</li>
</ul>
<p>Note: if blocking stealing, the player must declare whether it is blocked using a Captain or an Inquisitor.</p>
<h2><a href="#2-player-variant" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="2-player-variant"></a>2 player variant</h2>
<p>To play coup with 2 players, I recommend to use the following 2 additional rules</p>
<h3><a href="#call-the-coup" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="call-the-coup"></a>Call the Coup</h3>
<p>When a player performs the coup action, they must name a specific character to kill.
If the other player has that character, it is revealed and it dies as normal.</p>
<p>If the player does not have that specific character, that player reveals all of their character cards.
That player does not loose any of their cards, but the player who called the coup does loose their 7 coins.
The player who reviled their hand draws 2 cards from the deck and then chooses 2 cards to shuffle back into the deck.</p>
<h3><a href="#5-lives-each" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="5-lives-each"></a>5 lives each</h3>
<p>Both players start with 2 characters, as normal.
But if a character dies, that player draws a new card.
When loosing their 4th or 5th card, that player does not draw any new cards.</p>
<!-- Content Injected to every content markdown footer -->
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>